Guide to the Jack Smith Papers MSS.440
Fales Library and Special Collections
Jack Smith Papers
1891-1990, undated
1963-1985
Fales Library and Special Collections
Barbara Gladstone Gallery
Smith, Jack, 1932-1989
MSS.440
20.7 Linear Feet in eight manuscript boxes, one half manuscript box, ten record cartons, five oversize flat boxes, and two flat file folders.
Jack Smith (1932-1989) was a New York-based actor, filmmaker, and photographer known for his pioneering influence in experimental filmmaking and performance art. Smith's low-budget productions employed camp and kitsch aesthetics, including his best known film, Flaming Creatures. In addition to creating his own works, Smith appeared as an actor in productions by Andy Warhol and Robert Wilson. Smith died in 1989 from AIDS-related pneumonia. This collection consists of materials created by Smith throughout the course of his career as an artist, actor, filmmaker, and photographer. The majority of the collection consists of Smith's notes, scripts, drawings, flyers, and posters for his films and performance pieces, dating from the early 1960s through the late 1980s. The collection documents not only Smith's career and creative process, but also the larger landscape of underground cinema and performance art in the 1970s and 1980s.
Scope and Contents
This collection consists of materials created by Jack Smith throughout the course of his career as an artist, actor, filmmaker, and photographer from the 1960s to the late 1980s. Materials include scripts and notes on his films and performance pieces; and drawings, photographs, and collages used for flyers and posters for his performances. The influence of Smith's disagreement with Jonas Mekas, Smith's idolization of Maria Montez, and his work with Mario Montez is evident throughout his work. Other items in the collection include subject files and books on film-making, time periods and locations that influenced Smith, health, nutrition, and fitness; address books, his Rolodex, and mailing lists for his performances; financial material, including bank statements, investment statements, and tax records on a property Smith owned in Arizona; identification cards; and a small amount of correspondence. The majority of the collection consists of Smith's flyers and posters for his performances and notes on everything from ideas for new films and performances to lists of errands and chores.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open to researchers. Please contact the Fales Library and Special Collections, fales.library@nyu.edu, 212-998-2596.
Related Materials
For more information on Jack Smith, see the Ed Leffingwell Jack Smith Curatorial Files (call number MSS 380), which contain materials associated with Leffingwell's organization of the exhibition "Jack Smith: Flaming Creature" at MoMA PS1 in New York in 1997-1998 and associated printed matter, including material created by Jack Smith.
Other collections related to Smith include the John Vaccaro and the Play-House of the Ridiculous Papers (call number MSS 321) and the Serpent's Tail/High Risk Archive (call number MSS 086).
Custodial History
Prior to and following Smith's death, his personal papers were co-managed by New York performance artist Penny Arcade and film historian J. Hoberman through The Plaster Foundation, Inc. In January 2004, the New York Surrogate Court ordered Arcade and Hoberman to return the collection to Smith's sister, Sue Slater, resulting in an extended series of legal disputes. Despite claims from Arcade and Hoberman stating that Slater did not respond to their earlier attempts at communication, the collection was awarded to Slater. They refused to surrender the collection until 2008 when it was purchased from Smith's estate by the Gladstone Gallery. In July 2015, the Gallery donated this collection, which represents a portion of the original collection, to the Fales Library & Special Collections.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Donated by Gladstone Gallery in July 2015. The accession number associated with this gift is 2014.440.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged in six series, with the materials arranged in alphabetical order within series I, IV, and V. Series II is arranged into two broad topics, Health and Source Material, with no further arrangement within these topics. Series III and VI have not be arranged. The series are as follows:
Series I. Films and Performances, Series II. Subject Files, Series III. Books, Series IV. Business Records, Series V. Personal Items, and Series VI. Exhibition and Writings on Jack Smith.
Biographical note
Jack Smith (1932-1989) was a New York-based filmmaker, photographer, and actor known for his pioneering influence in experimental filmmaking and performance art. Smith moved to New York City in 1953, where he attended film classes at the City College of New York and worked as a photographer. He worked as an actor and assistant with Ken Jacobs for two years before making his first film, Scotch Tape, in 1959.
Smith created his most well-known film, Flaming Creatures, in 1963. The film was confiscated by the New York Police Department and banned throughout the United States due to nudity and charges of obscenity, and was later ruled obscene by a New York Criminal Court. Jonas Mekas, a friend of Smith's and the founder of the journal Film Culture and the Anthology Film Archives, championed the film and, despite the ban, screened it in theaters and hotel rooms around the country and at the Knokke-le-Zoute film festival in Belgium in 1964. This led to an argument between the two, as Smith believed that Mekas was responsible for the confiscation of the film as well as its notoriety. Mekas disagreed with Smith's practice of constantly re-editing his work, fearing that this would alter the original genius of the work, and used this to defend his possession of the film. As a result of this disagreement, Smith never produced another film in entirety as he was constantly editing his work, even while he was screening it. He also refused to have his work out of his possession. Many of his subsequent works focused on Mekas, including I Was a Mekas Collaborator, Death in Uncle Archives' Vault, and his adaptation of The Critic by Richard Brinsley Sheridan, variously titled The Critic, The Lobsters, Lucky Landlordism of Roachcrust, and Lucky Landlordism of Lotusland.
Actress Maria Montez was another profound influence on Smith's work. Known as the Queen of Technicolor, she was the star of Universal's Technicolor adventure movies filmed in the 1940s. Smith's performances, sets, and costumes were influenced by Montez and the atmosphere of her films. In the early 1960s, Smith convinced the young drag queen Rene Rivera to adopt the name Mario Montez in homage to Maria Montez. Mario starred in Flaming Creatures and other Smith performances, before becoming one of Andy Warhol's superstars.
Throughout the late 1960s and into the mid-1980s, Smith began to focus more on performance art and combined live performances with screenings of his films and slideshows. In addition to the Mekas inspired performances, shows created during this time period include Death of a Penguin, The Secret of Rented Island, Sinbad and the Rented World, No President, and I Was a Male Yvonne De Carlo for the Lucky Landlord Underground. Smith also published essays and short stories in Film Culture and other periodicals and appeared as an actor in productions by Andy Warhol, Robert Wilson, and Ken Jacobs.
Smith died in 1989 from AIDS-related pneumonia. His influence has been identified in genres of experimental filmmaking and performance art on the broad scale, and specifically in the works of Warhol, John Waters, Laurie Anderson, and Cindy Sherman.
Appraisal
Duplicates of flyers and posters for Smith's films and performances were weeded. Newspaper and magazine clippings and books not relevant to Smith's interests or work were weeded. Smith's clothing and receipts were determined to be of low research value and were deaccessioned.
Avant-garde films.; Photographers -- United States.; Artists -- New York (State) -- New York.; Color photographs.; Collages (visual works); Negatives (photographic); Experimental theater -- 20th century; AIDS (Disease); Independent filmmakers -- United States.; Fliers (printed matter); Performance art -- New York (State) -- New York.; Performance artists.; Gay artists -- United States; Notebooks; Flip books.; Posters.; Passports.; Ledgers (account books); Notes.; Motion picture producers and directors.; Montez, Maria, 1912-1951; Montez, Mario, 1935-2013; Mekas, Jonas; Barbara Gladstone Gallery
- Series I. Films, Performances, and Artwork, 1961-1989, undated; 8.3 Linear Feet in six manuscript boxes and four oversize flat boxes.
  Arrangement
  This series is arranged alphabetically by title of work, with subjects, formats, and alphabetical ranges interfiled. Works that have a substantial amount of material are listed by title; smaller ranges of material are filed together and listed under alphabetical ranges of titles included therein. Notes, scripts, drawings, flyers, posters, clippings and correspondence for each film, performance, or artwork are organized together intellectually but may be physically housed separately due to size or condition of the material.
  Scope and Content
  This series includes materials used in the creation of Smith's films and performance pieces, including scripts, notes, drawings, photographs, collages, flyers, posters, metal plates and mylar proofs for offset lithography, clippings, and correspondence. Included in the Flaming Creatures material are Smith's journal kept during the filming, a letter written by Smith to the Village Voice regarding the film, flyers for screenings, and notes on Jonas Mekas and his distribution of the film. The influence of Smith's disagreement with Mekas is evident throughout this series and includes flyers, mylar proofs, and offset lithography plates for I Was a Mekas Collaborator and How Can Uncle Fishhook Have a Free Bicentennial Zombie Underground?; flyers, notes, and scripts for Smith's adaptation of Richard Brinsley Sheridan's The Critic, variously titled The Critic, The Lobsters, Lucky Landlordism of Roachcrust, and Lucky Landlordism of Lotusland; and flyers for Death in Uncle Archives' Vault. Maria Montez is another influence found throughout the series, in particular in Memoirs of Maria Montez, or Wait for Me at the Bottom of the Pool and throughout Smith's notes, untitled writings, and untitled artworks. Notes, scripts, and flyers regarding Mario Montez performances can also be found throughout the series, including Normal Love, Flaming Creatures, and No President.
  Other material in this series includes script pages and correspondence regarding Normal Love and Normal Fantasy; posters, programs, and correspondence regarding film series and festivals that included screenings or performances by Smith; and original artwork and collages used by Smith to promote his performances. There are materials from a handful of productions written and directed by other artists in which Smith performed or attended. The bulk of the series consists of loose notes and notebooks, which include lists of titles for works; to-do lists and shopping lists; and ideas for new films or writings. In addition to these notes are longer pieces of untitled writing, of two paragraphs or more. Untitled artwork not related to Smith's artwork for his films and performances includes photographs, drawings, and collages, and an untitled mixed media art piece found in an envelope and assumed to be an artwork created by Smith.
  Other productions represented in this series include The Secret of Rented Island, Smith's adaptation of Henrik Ibsen's Ghosts; No President or The Kidnapping and Auctioning of Wendell Willkie by the Love Bandit; Death of a Penguin; Impacted Croissants of Outer Space; Sinbad in the Rented World, Smith's adaptation of William Shakespeare's Hamlet; The White Pig of the Medina; and I Was a Male Yvonne De Carlo for the Lucky Landlord Underground. Materials date from the late 1960s to the late 1980s.
  - A-Bi, 1968, 1979, undated (Box 11, Folder 11, Box 9, Folder 1-2, Folder 1, Box 1)
  - Brassieres of Atlantis, 1969 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Brassieres of B-Claptailism of L, 1968, 1978, undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Buzzards over Bagdad flipbook, 1966 (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - Claptailism of Palmola Economic Spectacle, 1971 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Clash of the Brassiere Goddesses, 1984 (Box 1, Folder 5, Box 9, Folder 4)
  - Clipping collages, 1972, 1979-1985, undated (Box 1, Folder 6, Box 9, Folder 5-6)
  - Clippings, 1963-1989, undated (Box Shared Fales 001, Folder 2, Box 11, Folder 10, Box 1, Folder 7-8, Box 9, Folder 7)
  - Collage material, Undated (Box 1, Folder 9-10, Box 9, Folder 8)
  - Con-Cou, 1977-1979, undated (Box 1, Folder 11, Box 9, Folder 9)
  - Crab Ogress of Jingola, Undated (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - The Critic, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 13-15, Box 9, Folder 10)
  - Cu-Fe, 1970-1985, undated (Box 1, Folder 16, Box 9, Folder 11-12, Box 11, Folder 2-3)
  - Film festivals and lectures, 1976-1985, undated (Box 2, Folder 1-2, Box 11, Folder 4, Box Shared Fales 001, Folder 2)
  - Flaming Creatures, 1961-1964, 1983-1985, undated (Box 2, Folder 3-4, Box 11, Folder 4)
  - Gala Party and Lobster Moon Pageant, 1968 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - The Great Moldy Triumph, 1963 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - H-In, 1963, 1975-1984, undated (Box 11, Folder 5, Box 10, Folder 1-2, Folder 12, Box 2, Folder 7, Box Shared Fales 001, Folder 5-6)
  - Irrational Landlordism of Bagdad, 1977 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Is-L, 1966-1970, undated (Box 10, Folder 2, Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Lucky Landlordism of Lotusland, 1973 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Lucky Landlordism of Roachcrust, 1973 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Memoirs of Maria Montez, or Wait for Me at the Bottom of the Pool, 1963 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Miracle at Farblonjet, Undated (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - No President, 1969 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Normal Love, 1963-1968, 1974, 1989, undated (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Notebooks, 1974-1987, undated (Box 3, Folder 3-6, Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Notes, 1969-1988, undated (Box 5, Folder 1-2, Box 11, Folder 6, Box 10, Folder 3, Box 4, Folder 1-8, Box 3, Folder 7-10, Box Shared Fales 001, Folder 2)
  - O-Pe, 1973-1981, undated (Box 11, Folder 7, Box 10, Folder 4, Box 5, Folder 3)
  - "'Pink Flamingos' Formulas in Focus", 1973 (Box 5, Folder 4, Box 10)
  - Pir-Poo, 1986, undated (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Portfolio, Undated (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Press packet, 1985 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Press R-Secret, 1965, 1973-1976, undated (Box 10, Folder 5, Box 5, Folder 8, Box Shared Fales 001, Folder 2)
  - Secret of Rented Island, 1976 (Box 11, Folder 7, Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Secrets of t-Sh, 1971-1972, undated (Box 10, Folder 5, Box 5, Folder 10, Box 11, Folder 7)
  - Sinbad and the 7 Labors of Uranus, Undated (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Sinbad in the Rented World, 1972-1984 (Box 10, Folder 6, Box 5, Folder 12, Folder 17)
  - Sinbad S-Sp, 1982-1984, undated (Box 10, Folder 6, Box 5, Folder 13)
  - Stationery, Undated (Box 10, Folder 6, Box 5, Folder 14)
  - Stencils and lettering, Undated (Box 6, Folder 1, Box 5, Folder 15)
  - Sy-Unh, 1975, undated (Box 10, Folder 7, Box 11, Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Untitled artwork, Undated (Box 11, Folder 8, Box 10, Folder 8-9, Box 6, Folder 3-4, Box Shared Fales 001)
  - Untitled mixed media art piece, Undated (Box 19, Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Untitled writings, Undated (Box 6, Folder 6-7)
  - V-Wha, 1969, 1981, undated (Box 10, Folder 10, Box 6, Folder 8)
  - The White Pig of the Medina, Undated (Box 11, Folder 8, Box 6, Folder 9-10)
  - Wi-Won, Undated (Box 6, Folder 11)
  - Works and performances by other artists, 1971-1988, undated (Box 6, Folder 12-13, Box 11, Folder 8)
- Series II. Subject Files, 1960-1989, undated; 3.1 Linear Feet in one and a half record cartons, one manuscript box, and eight oversize folders.
  This series is arranged into two broad topics, Health and Source Material.
  This series contains clippings from newspapers and magazines, with some full issues, on topics of interest to Smith. They are divided into two broad topics, Health and Source Material. Health includes nutrition, exercise, hair loss, HIV/AIDS, and mental wellness. Source Material includes films and filmmaking, photography, the Golden Age of Hollywood, and beaches and deserts (in particular Hawaii, North Africa, and the Middle East). The clippings contain articles as well as images used in collages or as inspiration for settings in his films and performances. Materials date from the late 1960s to the 1980s, with the bulk from the early to mid 1980s.
  - Health, 1964-1989, undated; 1984-1989; 0.7 Linear Feet in half of a record carton and three oversize folders. (Box 21, Folder 1-10, Box 20, Folder 1-3)
  - Source material, 1960-1989, undated; 1969-1981; 2.3 Linear Feet in one record carton, one manuscript box, and five oversize folders. (Box 21, Folder 11-21, Box 22, Folder 1-9, Box 20, Folder 4-6, Box 10, Folder 12, Box 11, Folder 9, Box 23, Folder 1-7)
- Series III. Books, 1891-1987, undated; 1968-1978; 7 Linear Feet in seven record cartons.
  This series has not been arranged.
  This series contains books from Smith's library and includes fiction and nonfiction titles. Agatha Christie and Sax Rohmer books constitute the bulk of the fiction titles, with other authors including Washington Irving, William Shakespeare, Sinclair Lewis, Jorge Amado, Charles Dickens, and Henry Green. Nonfiction topics include the Alhambra, Hawaii, Arabic art, Hollywood, typography, border design, exercise, and nutrition. Materials date from the late 1890s to the mid-1980s, with the bulk dating from 1968 to 1978.
  - Books, 1891-1987, undated (Box 17, Box 16, Box 18, Box 13, Box 12, Box 15, Box 14)
- Series IV. Business and Financial Records, 1962-1990, undated; 1971-1985; 1.1 Linear Feet in one and a half manuscript boxes and one record carton.
  This series is arranged in alphabetical order, with type of document, correspondent, and folder titles created by Smith interfiled together.
  This series contains Smith's bank and investment statements; a small amount correspondence with friends, as well as film and cultural organizations; correspondence, notes, and flyers regarding Smith's legal dealings with his landlords; ledgers, some of which detail Smith's income and expenses from the Film-makers' Cooperative for 1964-1965, for screenings of Flaming Creatures; grant applications in support of Sinbad in the Rented World; address books, mailing lists, and a Rolodex; and tax records for Smith's property in Apache County, Arizona. Materials date from 1962 to 1990, with the bulk dating between 1971-1985.
  - Address book/flip book, Undated (Box 6, Folder 14)
  - American Federation of Arts, 1983-1984 (Box 6, Folder 15)
  - Apartment, 1981-1987, undated (Box 6, Folder 16)
  - Arriflex Corporation, 1982-1984 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Bank records, 1976-1990 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, 1962-1967, 1970-1974, 1980-1989, undated (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Creative Artists Public Program, 1980-1982 (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Film-makers' Cooperative, 1963-1971 (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Investments, 1977-1989 (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Ledgers, 1985-1986 (Box 7, Folder 7-8)
  - Mailing lists, Undated (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - National Endowment for the Arts, 1981-1985 (Box 7, Folder 10-11)
  - New American Cinema Group, 1975-1976 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Opportunities, Undated (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Property in Apache County, Arizona, 1984-1989 (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Rolodex, Undated (Box 22)
  - Theatres to work in, 1985, undated (Box 8, Folder 4)
- Series V. Personal Items, 1974-1989, undated; 1988-1989; 0.2 Linear Feet in three folders and one oversize folder.
  This series is arranged alphabetically by type of document.
  This series consists of Smith's passports and identification cards; his medical records; an invitation for his memorial in 1989; and a photograph of Smith with three unidentified men. The medical records include discharge information and membership materials from the Gay Men's Health Crisis (GMHC). Materials date from the 1974 to 1989, with the bulk of the materials dating between 1988-1989.
  - Identification cards and passports, 1974-1989, undated (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - Medical records, 1988-1989 (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - Memorial invitation, 1989 (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - Photograph of Smith with three unidentified friends at Hawaii Kai restaurant, Undated (Box 10, Folder 11)
- Series VI. Exhibition and Writings on Jack Smith, 1997; 1 Linear Feet in one record carton. (Box 19)
  This series contains some of the files kept by Edward G. Leffingwell and others during the planning of MoMA PS1's 1997-1998 exhibit, Jack Smith: Flaming Creature. The files contain photocopies of Smith's letters, scripts, photographs, and notes used in the exhibit, and notes and sketches from exhibit planning. This series also includes notes on essays and copies of Smith's notes and artwork to be published in Wait For Me at the Bottom of the Pool: The Writings of Jack Smith, co-edited by Leffingwell and J. Hoberman.